this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
[Music]
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
this is Robert lumen I'm at the SF
conference in San Francisco I am joined
by Dwight Merriman Dwight is the CEO and
co-founder of 10gen the industry sponsor
of the open-source database
Dwight welcome to software engineering
radio Thank You Dwight
I will be talking with you about no
sequel and database first please
tell the listeners a little bit about
your background so my background is
technical I started out as a developer I
was the co-founder at double-click and
CTO at double-click built the original
technology there and after toe after
double-click started some new companies
including Tenjin which I'm working on
now which is the which originated and
and sponsors the MongoDB project you've
given a presentation that's available on
the internet called the transition to a
non relational world why is the world
moving in that direction
the original catalyst for that is the
desire for horizontal scalability so
scaling a traditional relational
database horizontally is a very hard
problem distributed joins are very hard
to do if you don't make any assumptions
about the schema in addition distributed
transactions are expensive to do so
there is a need for data storage
solutions in my opinion that scale
horizontally easily and if we leave out
joins and complex transactions we can do
that so these new non-relational
solutions that's their characteristic
now that's why the space got started
that was the catalyst was really desire
for horizontal scalability but in
addition I think there's an opportunity
to innovate around things like data
models now that we're doing something
that isn't relational to get some other
benefits including ease of development
why relational database has come to
dominate the storage market over the
last 20 years that's a good question
you know relational is 40 years old as a
theory so it's it's got to be one of the
most long-lived and successful
technologies in history I can't think
anything more so the and they worked
really well you know I think one of the
key things was there is a significant
benefit to decoupling the data storage
concept and and data model from the
program and the code right so and you
know and enterprises have many
applications and use many programming
languages and those languages change
over time you know every few years
there's a new programming language so we
don't want our data to be too tightly
coupled to the code and I think in the
early days of object databases that was
a bit of an issue the nice thing with
relational is you know there are no
relational programming languages you
know where the you know where you have
relation as a data type really so it's
it's it's nicely separated from from the
coding environment which apparently
almost paradoxically turns out to be
kind of useful because you're gonna have
so many different pieces of code in so
many different languages and the codes
complicated so if I have to know the
code to know the data that would be a
problem in addition you know it's turned
out that sequel is is was a really
powerful thing which let's have a nice
interface between client and server of
these applications and have some
standardization around that so that was
great and and that was obviously built
on top of relational concepts you said
one of the key drivers of movement away
from relational is the need to scale out
discuss the scaling issues that you run
into with a relational data store well
most relational databases like if you
said I want to have a 10 node database
cluster that looks like one logical
machine you can't do it I mean there are
some you can in particular there are a
number solutions in the data warehousing
and business intelligence space which
facilitate that so in that space I
actually think it's ok but that's a
special problem where it just turns out
that the problem is easier there but on
things that they're more let's say
online or old TP oriented it's very
difficult to build clusters and and
remain really two types of clusters one
just clusters on land
but to than clusters that are in
multiple data centers and things like
that - that's even worse so you know
it's just it's very hard to make joins
distributed joins fast you've talked
about scaling and scaling out is high
availability of the web world another
driving factor in the move away from
relational stores I think it is I think
there are pretty good high availability
solutions for traditional databases I
think people are pushing that a little
further in in the in this new non
relational space so I think it's it's
more of a driver around scale and then
as as people are willing to make the
conceptual leap on around this because
of the need to scale and they're finding
some other benefits you know the the the
general trend in computer architectures
are such that you're gonna need to scale
horizontally for a long time
vertical scaling was very feasible right
we could get a bigger box for Oracle and
that's great but what's happening is now
that you know CPU cores aren't getting
faster so you can't get a faster CPU
core but I can give you a thousand cores
really cheap but that means I kind of
need horizontal scaling that so with
cloud type services there's more of an
economic force driving people to want to
deploy on clusters of low-powered yes so
cloud computing there there's a really
direct synergy between it and some of
these new technologies
you know cloud computing horizontal
scaling is is a key attribute of cloud
computing and elasticity and you know we
don't really have that in traditional
databases so you know you're getting on
something like Amazon ec2 you're really
getting kind of come out of like
hardware so they're really the way to
build a big system is use lots of boxes
not one giant box so there's definitely
a fit there and you know really the weak
link in cloud computing right now is the
data storage layer I mean some of these
new solutions are all young and the old
solutions don't map well to cloud
computing is it fair to say that you
look at relational databases as a
product class
they're all more or less doing the same
thing and they do it a little bit
differently but when you talk about no
sequel you're talking about a bigger
family of systems with more variability
there's a lot more variability I think
there is some variability in the
relational space especially if you look
at the reporting world where there's
been a lot of custom things done with
databases but it's far more homogeneous
than this no sequel space is and a big
reason for that is it's early with this
space right so it's there's an analogy I
think between what's happening right now
and no sequel to the early days of
relational and you had ingress and
Informix and Sybase and db2 and Oracle
and not even everyone was using sequel
as the query language there's a bunch of
relational databases that used other
query languages and then there was a bit
of a shakeout and then it turned out
there was a few winners and they all use
sequel and so we're in that same kind of
early shakeout phase you know it's
probably some of the products in the no
sequel space don't even exist yet that
will be popular in ten years and some of
the ones there today will eventually
kind of you know become informix or
something I suppose so but I think the
space as a whole with it's growing
really fast and it's really exciting in
the relational world there are
definitely some excellent open source
alternatives but some of the very big
players are pure commercial closed
source whereas in no sequel there is a
domination of open source models and
in-house databases like Amazon's DB that
are provided to you as a service by a
cloud provider do you see that
persisting or do you see large
commercial entities coming to dominate
space yeah it's very interesting you
know I when I look at the kind of the
most popular database segments I really
see what I think will be the most
popular segments and say five years I
see three things I see your traditional
online OTP style relational database
that'll still be there that'll still be
totally applicable for a set of use
cases it just won't be all use cases
which it used to be there's also a
segment which is really around data
analytics offline reporting
data warehousing business intelligence
that's a segment too that exists which
is distinct and which I think will stay
pretty relational but you a different
set of technologies from companies like
aster data and green plum and Vertica in
the third space I think we're going to
see massive massive use of five years
from now will be no sequel which will
really be these non relational or post
relational data stores that are
horizontally scalable and that are
suitable mainly for online data
operations within the non relational
space you've talked about classifying
the systems along several different axes
one of those axes is provided by the cap
theorem
I'd like to delve a little bit into the
cap theorem so we can understand it and
then use it to talk about different
types of data stores in brief what is
the cap theorem showing so the cap
theorem is a conjecture from Eric Brewer
that was then proven and became a
theorem which basically says in an in a
distributed system if you look at three
properties which are consistency
availability and tolerance to network
partitions so that's the C and the a and
the P you can't have all three at the
same time and there's a proof of this
and so another way to say that basically
so we're talking about distributed
systems here so there's a network
involved right so in the network
partitions part of the network is down
so what this really says is if the
network is broken your database is not
going to work
this is not surprising if it's a
distributed database however we do get a
pick what doesn't work means we can
choose either it's down or unavailable
in that situation or we can choose that
it's up but the the the results are not
strongly consistent right we have a
weaker consistency model not zero
consistency but some other weaker model
like eventual consistency you've shown a
triangle with the sides CA and P you can
think of each pair of properties as one
corner of the triangle but look to look
at those three corners
briefly so what does a CA data store
look like how does it behave yeah so so
basically a CA data store gives you
consistency and availability and then it
the question is then what happens if the
network partitions so if you get both of
those since we can't have all three that
probably means you get incorrect
operation so an example of a CA system
would be a single computer right so if
we run Oracle on one server we think of
it as having CNA at least for say a
client program running on that computer
but if you imagine say the memory bus is
losing data like you do a memory
operation and it fails that would be
kind of like a network partition and
then you would get basically incorrect
results so that's kind of what a CA
solution is so in a way CA doesn't even
make sense because we're fundamentally
here talking about distributed systems
that's the context of the cap theorem so
they're really they're I don't think
there really is such a thing as CA
system so we're really picking between
consistency or availability and there
may be a little bit of a dial between
them so we really are picking either CP
or ap and so you know sometimes people
will say cap theorem there's three sides
pick any two but I think that's actually
wrong it's either you know pick C or
pick a because you got to have P you got
it you you got to be able to tolerate a
network partition and not corrupt your
data basically talk a little bit then
between those two choices about the C
type system right so C type systems are
strongly consistent system so if in the
proof of a cap theorem its it talks
about ability to do atomic operations on
data entities so so so really you know
where you can do something like say
increment value atomically or do if
balance greater than ten balance equals
balance minus ten atomically those types
of things where if you had two
operations happening at the same time
and you don't handle the
serialization of those you then could
get an incorrect result of like say
negative ten or something like that so
so it's it's about there's two things
that come with the C of consistency that
with strong consistency it's mainly
about consistency of the order of
application of operations and atomicity
of those applications but it's also
about the data being fresh and
immediately consistent so that when when
you don't have strong consistency you
you typically lose two things one is you
lose ability to do atomic operations and
the other is that you can read old data
right so you can read temporarily stale
data you give an example of or some
examples of systems or products out
there that would fall into that C Class
well most traditional databases are in
the C Class right they support
transactions and and and give you you
know if somebody committed an operation
and you then do a read you will
guaranteed to see their effects of that
operation
among the no sequel databases are there
some systems that are organized around
that C class so it's interesting because
I think each of the products has an
architectural sweet spot or bias but to
some degree consistency is tunable so
for example if we take my sequel right
if you use my sequel on a single server
it's strongly consistent but if I do
master/slave asynchronous replication
with it and I do reads from the slave
that's eventually consistent behavior so
so it really depends how you set the
products up but but but there are
different styles of products there are
some which are strongly in the
eventually consistent camp there are
some that they're strongly biased
towards the strong consistency camp and
there are some which are more in the
middle so what does the a-class
data store look like so really a class
data store is trying to maximize
availability and what that probably
means is it's then
when it's configured as such an
eventually consistent system we're going
to come back to that term eventually
consistent that you've used a couple of
times could you give an example of a
problem that you've seen where you would
either choose a a class
or C class yeah so so let's let's start
with a class so systems which are
basically maximize availability and are
eventually consistent so the interesting
thing is people talk about cap a lot but
there are a couple of reasons to use
these eventually consistent systems one
is it does theoretically give you higher
availability in the face of network
partitions but you know it a lot of
network partitions are what I call
trivial network partitions right so if
if an entire data center goes dark and
you have three data centers well that's
a trivial partition you could failover
to one of your other data centers and
run from there because they're all the
clients in the one data center are down
right it's really the the non-trivial
partition is where the entire internet
you know the west coast of the US can
talk to the west coast of the US and the
East Coast can talk to the east coast
but they can't talk to each other right
that's a non-trivial partition that
would be harder and then you would if
you had eventual consistency in an
a-class system you would be happy but if
you lose a whole data center and you
have multiple data centers you can
handle it in either model generally so a
lot of partitions are trivial you know
losing a whole rack typically a trivial
network partition now that said so I
think the a that availability in the
aspect of eventual consistent a-class
systems is a little over weighted
however there is a pretty big benefit
which is the ability to have low latency
reads and writes in the multi data
center configuration it gives you that
right because you don't have to wait for
the data to across the other data
centers necessarily up front so so
latency is actually a key aspect of the
equation that cap doesn't capture at all
right so so we really I think it's
consistency availability and latency
I'm starting to think our that are some
of the key variables be fair say then
what the no sequel movement is saying is
we have this whole space of design
choices and we need to use the whole
space based on the problem and not just
default to a relational database it may
not take advantage of the problem that
you're trying to solve yeah the way I
think of it is just that as Michael
Stonebraker has said that one size fits
all is over we're gonna see some
specialization in databases now right
we're not just going to use one tool for
everything it's not you know we're not
going to use MongoDB for everything but
there's going to be the right tool for
the right problem and and and depending
on what you're doing that tool will vary
what sort of choices did you make with
MongoDB navigating the cap theorem
MongoDB is more in the C class so it's
sort of default configuration is
strongly consistent now we I in my the
way I define those sequel is I think all
the solutions there have do not do joins
and do not do complex transactions
because if you leave those two things
out horizontal scalability is then very
feasible so we don't do those two things
but what we're really trying to do is
beyond that keep as many characteristics
of a traditional databases if we can so
we're gonna leave out what we have to to
get horizontal scalability but keep
everything else so in some ways it's
very traditional you know we have you
know we have secondary indexes we
support ad hoc queries we support
sorting so so so there's a lot of of
those things that you expect in the
database are still there and which may
not be surprising but then if you look
at some of the other products that's
it's a it's a very different approach to
the problem so our approach is is more
in the strong consistency camp so you
can do atomic operations in MongoDB so
for we let you do them on single data
objects right so we do not give you
complex transactional semantics but we
give you simple transactional semantics
we can do that and still scale
horizontally but having simple atomicity
actually lets you do a lot of use cases
obviously there's some where you would
need
more than that but then there's some
where you don't need any atomicity at
all but there's a bunch which that that
middle ground solves and we want to be
able to capture what are people doing
with they're doing a lot I think the the
biggest use case in the whole new no
sequel space is just building web
infrastructure and and using these
products as operational data store web
infrastructure storing content of
website user session info user profile
info logins real-time performance
counters logging data storage those are
all common uses of the of these systems
storing images videos but it most online
problems with data storage that are not
highly transactional they're a really
good fit for I think they're not as
oriented towards reporting you can do
reporting with these private systems but
it's just question of is it actually the
best tool for that problem and sometimes
it's not I think there's some very good
reporting solutions in the relational in
the sequel space so that we've seen a
lot there but you know I'm also just any
problem where you need massive scale or
speed people like it for also people
people like these things for problems
where they want fast development so for
example with MongoDB
it's a JSON database it's basically has
dynamic schemas so you can put JSON
objects in the collection and you know
if you want to add a new field to one of
these objects that's not on the other
objects that's okay you don't have to
run an alter table style command so
schema migration work is vastly reduced
and that fits really well with agile
development you know if you're doing a
release a day you don't want to do a
database migration scripts a day so
that's a really good fit are you seeing
a lot more within a single web
application or a single business people
are mixing and matching multiple data
storage solutions based on the needs of
a particular service yes so I think
large organizations will use several
products so if I am a fortune 1000
company I would want if I were CIO there
I would definitely
something like Oracle for certain things
for certain ulti problems OTP problems
they're highly transactional I would use
a no sequel solution like MongoDB
for a lot of problems where I need fast
real-time reads and writes of an online
data storage more schema and data
flexibility and really has to be in
scale and to make development easy and
then I would also get something like
Astra data or green plum or Vertica and
use that for my data warehouse and bi
work now that said if I'm a small
organization though I may not use all
that things so we have a lot of users
today who are building websites and 100%
of their data is stored in and
that's the only thing they're using the
and that even includes their images
their videos and then you put anything
in the file system so it's just kind of
interesting but I think as as companies
get bigger you'll use a broader range of
solutions just cuz you had to scale that
it makes sense get a little more
specialized we've talked a little bit
about the weakening of consistency you
have some very interesting articles on
your blog about a range of consistency
models everyone should go to the
DB blog and read the six series of six
blog posts about consistency and you can
see the diagram there it's like to go
through these starting at the most
consistent and work up give a brief
description of each one there's multi
entity transactions I think I know what
that is yeah so that's strong
consistency with full transactions so
you know debit object debit a and credit
B and do it atomically is a transaction
so that's your classic database
transactions you do with things like
Oracle or with my sequel with a ODB you
have the strong consistency on a single
entity right so this is what you can do
with MongoDB so we'll let you do you
know if you could debit a and credit B
and MongoDB
if and only if they're in the same
object so if those are in both in the
same JSON object you can do that atomic
but if they were in different object
data objects that would be multi entity
and you couldn't do that so it you can
do atomic operations on single objects
in MongoDB immediate consistency that is
where basically if someone's done a
right I'm guaranteed to see the results
of that right immediately is what we
mean by that however that is different
from having atomicity because I could
have immediate consistency but not
atomicity read your own rights read your
own rights consistency so what that
means is this is a looser form of
consistency which is saying that it may
take a while for a right to be viewable
by everyone but it's saying that if you
did the right you're guaranteed that you
will see it and that's very useful
that's a very useful semantics to happen
having an eventually consistent system
to help right create correct programs if
you're the client and you've written
something you don't have to think about
waiting around for your own right to the
eventually consistent right so it so a
good example is you know if I let's say
I go on to my social networking side and
I change my profile picture right and
well if it takes a few seconds for that
to show up for other users who view my
profile that's fine but if then when I
hit OK and submit that I go back to my
homepage and I see my old picture I will
be very confused so read my own right it
will avoid the confusion it's ok if
other people see the old picture because
they didn't know the update happened it
will not create confusion for them in
this particular case now but the
interesting thing to remember there on
read your own rights is sort of what's
the scope who's the who is the you who's
reading their own rights it was the
actual the user of the website so it's
not just a single you know HTTP request
to an app server it was actually the
next request that it was for the same
user where we wanted to read our own
right and so that can actually be kind
of hard to implement sometimes because
the load balancer may send the next
request to a different machine there's
MongoDB provide that if you have strong
consistency you'll automatically have
read your own right consistency because
and you'll automatically have immediate
consistency so there's
there's sort of a hierarchy here a
little bit and there's actually a couple
edge cases where you might have one
thing or not the other monotonic read
consistency so monotonic read
consistency is an eventual consistent
system which has the additional property
that for a given reader if they've seen
a read they will then never see an older
copy of that data item so with pure
eventual consistency it's possible that
you know let's say that we have some
data into the X right and let's say
somebody writes one to it and then one
second later they write to one secondly
they write three one second layer they
write four if you have pure eventual
consistency you might read that as the
three read it as a one read it as a to
read it as a two and then read it as a
four I mean them maybe read it to
support forever as you hit the
consistency eventually so I got but I
got values in a strange order right
which could be semantically confusing
depending on what was happening so with
monotonic read consistency if those
reads if those rights had happen in that
sequence one two three four over time 2x
you know I may not see the most
up-to-date copy instantly I may not see
the four but if I see the two I'll never
see anything earlier than the two again
that's what monotonic read consistency
means so that actually intuitively makes
a lot more sense to the programmer than
just pure eventually consistency you
know one way to think about it is if if
you had let's say you had we're using my
sequel and you said that master-slave
replication and you had ten slave
machines doing asynchronous replication
from the master and so if you read from
the slaves it's eventually consistent
and maybe as a client you just read from
a random slave because you're just
trying to distribute the load but each
server each slave could be at a
different point in applying the logs
asynchronously from the master so you
could get nan you could get results that
are not monotonic leary consistent in
that configuration what I would take
away from this as a architect then is I
need to think about how much consistency
do I need for an application every
increase in consistent
see I pay for by make failure scenarios
a little bit more difficult or
increasing the possibility of downtime
in insert failure cases right when you
have higher consistency you
theoretically lose a little bit of
availability and you also lose latency
in multi data center configurations what
you gain is clear and intuitive
semantics for the database so that's
really the trade-off so I think with
eventual consistency you can solve many
problems with it but the semantics are
surprising so the developer needs to
really think about what do I need is
eventual consistency sufficient or maybe
maybe eventual consistency with
monotonic reads I can solve the problem
or maybe if I have read your own writes
like for the for the for the picture
example that would be fine or maybe I
need more than that you know maybe I
need a meet at consistency or maybe I
need atomicity or maybe any full
transactions so the the stronger the
consistency is the lazier we can be as
programmers you have to work harder the
looser you make it and I think all these
modes are useful I like it as a I like
strong consistency as a default though
because it has the least surprising
semantics you know we should really be
prepared to put on our thinking caps and
say hey and let me make sure I'm getting
this right when we move to the looser
consistency models so when you say the
programmer has to work harder what do
you mean by that
well there's actually a couple ways one
is you just got to be careful that you
your design is correct so for example if
you just say okay I'm gonna use an
eventual consistency no see I'm gonna
use Amazon simple DB in eventual
consistency mode
it actually has tunable consistency now
but let's say you use the defaults and
you know you let someone update their
profile picture well then they go back
to their homepage and they see the rope
old profile photo they're confused well
you know having the user confused is bad
that in the way could be a design bug
that said that the programmer think
about that or did they just kind of
assume it would be fine now that's an
example where there's a little bit of
pain because it was eventually
consistent the user was confused but the
world didn't end but there are actually
cases where it's more important
so a good example is let's say I'm I
have a site like Flickr and I choose who
can see my photos and I have a list of
those people let's say I go in and I
remove someone from the list of people
who can see my photos like my girlfriend
and then I post some new pictures that I
don't want her to see but if the system
is eventually consistent she still might
they're still there was a probability
greater than zero that she will see the
pictures which would be a huge problem
potentially so that's a scenario where
you definitely need a higher degree of
consistency to get the problem right so
the question is really it's not that
that's bad to have eventual consistency
it's just like oh oh yeah let's just not
use it for that particular problem but
it's really just those developers did we
really do the mental exercise to say yes
it's okay in this particular problem so
if I have a blog and people are
commenting on the blog and people see
blog posts out of order or they show up
later blog comments maybe that's not too
big of a deal right so on the blog
I think monotonic read consistency would
be really nice right because it would be
bad if i refresh the page and comments
disappeared that would be very confusing
to me but if but if you made a comment
and I didn't and I reload the page a
second later and it you see your comment
that's actually fine right because I
mean I could have loaded the page two
seconds earlier I went to see in the
comment it's no big deal
now however you would probably also want
read your own writes consistency because
if I make a comment on the blog and go
back to the page and I don't see my
comment I'm gonna be confused so really
a lot of times like so I think on the on
the blog commenting system eventual
consistency works but what I would
really want is read your own writes
consistency and monotonic read
consistency when you say that programmer
asked us to work harder what you mean is
we have to go through more yet scenarios
and say what if you would have had to
think about what I just said whereas you
know if you put all your comments in
Oracle you didn't actually have to do
any thinking you will get a non
surprising result you have also
discussed how we can classify these no
sequel solutions in terms of their data
storage model what are the primary plus
of storage models and I think this is a
important topic that hasn't been
discussed enough yet none of these
solutions are relational data model
right because we want to make horizontal
scaling easy with with relational it's
very hard to scale horizontally so what
all these no sequel solutions are saying
is let's not do relational let's make
the problem easy and then we can solve
it and that's what Google did with
BigTable that's what Amazon did with
dynamo that's what LinkedIn did with
Voldemort
they all said non-relational data store
so the question then though we know it's
not relational as a data model but then
what is the data model and I don't think
this has got enough tension yet so
there's a several choices one is just a
pure key value store and this is what
Amazon dynamo was so the model there is
primary key to value where the value is
just an opaque blob if you will of data
that we can't reach into so memcache D
is a key value store right it's not
persistent one but it's a key value
store so that's a key value data model
so that's really where things started
because that's the simplest thing you
could do so that's one data model and
that the really nice thing there is it's
so simple and then it becomes very easy
to scale very easy to make it fast right
memcache D is faster than basically
anything so but the limit there is that
it doesn't do very much right I can only
do a key value data model it's a very
specific thing other choices
so the BigTable data model is another
choice or variations on the big table
data model basically where you have
these sort of multi-dimensional tabular
tables things which have some column
flexibility kind of column or
characteristics to them so that's one
data model another data model is what
you might call document oriented
databases so this by document we don't
mean text document I think more like XML
document so a document with some
structure and in fact the way things are
going everyone is standardizing on JSON
JavaScript object notation for these
documents so we're really storing object
like data in the database in the
document oriented solutions and
specifically JSON format data
you know that there have been XML
databases around for a very long time
XML is another type of document yet I
would make a guess that these JSON
databases have already gained more
deployments in XML databases have been
much more successful would you agree
with I do and why is that well I think
it is a question of timing and what the
value proposition was so when the XML
databases came out I think part of the
proposition was easy way to store semi
structured data an easy way to store XML
and if you're doing a lot of web
services in XML this will be a good
thing for you but I think in practice
what people found is you know I get that
in my program my programs talking to the
relational database anyway I'll just
keep using that so that there weren't
giving you the horizontal scalability
generally which was the really the big
driver that's you know because
relational is so mature everyone knows
it everyone's been trained on it so to
move beyond that is is a pretty big
hurdle right but so I need a big value
proposition for that and getting
horizontal scalability is big enough one
that people will make the leap so I
think they're they just didn't have it
also you know XML is tedious you know
it's not easy to read JSON is Riis easy
to read for a programmer it looks just
like code except it's just the data part
if we have a standard for it of course
just like XML we have an RSC for JSON
every web developer knows it because you
have to know it to build web apps so
it's a very convenient language
independent format for object like data
you say that JSON document oriented
databases suffered all from the lack of
anything like a DTD or an XML schema to
ensure the Lydda T of the entries that's
a great question it's possible of course
with in these JSON databases that to add
some sort of a schema check before you
change the data so you could make them
strictly scheme it if you wanted to the
and and I in the early days of I
assumed that we would do that at some
point the interesting thing is that
people aren't asking me for that so I
thought we would have done it by now but
we haven't because empirically in
practice
they're not having problems with noisy
data right so the programmer it's very
common in a collection which is a
MongoDB you have collections of JSON
documents to have a highly homogenous
set of fields for all the JSON objects
in one collection although there's no
requirement for that you know what's
nice is then you want to add a new field
you can add it to one object and none of
the others you don't have to run alter
table which is impossible once you get
to a certain scale anyway so it's very
nice but the data actually it tends to
just stay clean by itself and a good
analogy perhaps is to with dynamically
typed programming languages right so in
a dynamically typed programming language
a lot of errors are called at runtime
when the types don't match right and so
you know my first reaction to that when
I first heard of that you know 20-some
years ago as wow that sounds really
scary but it turns out there's a place
for that you know and it makes
development easier there's also a place
for statically type you know MongoDB is
written in C++ I like that is statically
typed there but I also can see why
someone would want to use Ruby or Lisp
which are dynamically typed so so here I
think there's a little bit of analogy
there to having kind of more dynamic
typing in database has some benefits a
good example is let's say you want to
store object type data in the database
and you have an inheritance hierarchy
for your objects right so I have a base
class and some subclasses in a JSON
database if if I don't have a tight
schema it's very easy for me to put all
those objects which are everything that
descends from the base class in one
collection because the fact that you
know subclass B had an extra field and
it's no problem it just sits there and
everybody's happy so it actually makes
certain data mapping problems quite easy
you gave a talk this morning about
schema design and MongoDB talked about
choice between linking or embedding tell
us about that right so links are really
your kind of like a traditional database
foreign key between you know you know
you know record a points the record be
somewhere else in the database
and or in an object database you have
links or references between objects
right so in an object database there's a
lot of linking in your old-style object
database system where you just have a
big graph of links between objects that
you persist the the approach with these
JSON databases is radically different
which is that basically you can link but
you if you want to link you got to do it
yourself client-side by doing an extra
request back to the server so if you
know I need to do some tasks and I need
to traverse one or two lengths and I'm
on the land with the database server and
it takes me a millisecond round-trip to
talk to the database okay that's a
couple milliseconds that's fine but if I
need to traverse a thousand links things
are going to get slow so I wouldn't want
to do that so a little bit is okay and
it helps me solve problems but a lot
would be bad so the way what we do
instead of linking is we do embedding so
we build relatively rich documents in
JSON with a fair degree of nesting of
objects within objects and arrays of
objects within objects so you've
explained already why can't do it join
and have horizontal scalability very
easily what extent would you say that
all the joining that people are doing in
relational databases is driven by the
fact that they've normalized their data
and that might not be even the most
natural way to organize their data part
of it is that and then part of it is
another reason which is just it's valid
fundamental entity relationship
connections between entities but yes you
know when you have an order object in an
order line item table and you're joining
those you know you're putting back
together or what conceptually was one
thing right that we had disassembled in
the database so he had we've taken it
apart to a radical extent just to make
it fit in with relational model
efficiently so that is an example
something that was being joined that you
would join that's sort of artificial but
you know when you you know when you say
you know give me give me the total
amount of dollars this customer has ever
spent and I need their join against the
orders table to get that you know that
makes a lot of sense
speakers at your conference here this
morning said I don't want to have to
have an elephant sit on my ADA before I
put yeah and and that's funny the you
know definitely a lot of that
quote-unquote impedance mismatch between
object and relational goes away when you
use a JSON data store now the
interesting thing is that you still do
schema design and there's still
discipline around that you know we still
define collections in we still
define indexes and we still choose water
the fields going to be in these objects
so there's still a discipline around
that and how we structure the data which
is relevant so it's actually quite
different from the object databases
where you said it kind of said my
program defines the structure of the
data now persist it right because we
think here it's actually important to
say I want to put the data in the
database in the format that is intuitive
to a reader of the database who doesn't
know the program code are many different
programming languages are popular web
framework offering anything like a
mapping layer as are so common with
relational databases to move the data in
and out yeah so there's a lot of
frameworks such as mapper for Ruby
which do mapping from you know an active
record like thing for example which
mapper is down to JSON type
serialization in the so that still
exists however that mapping layer gets
an order of magnitude thinner so we're
still mapping and there's still some you
know model frameworks and that kind of
stuff but the complexity of those
mapping layers is radically reduced
because the the things we're mapping
between are already pretty darn close
your colleague Richard crater has a
presentation where he says you can
organize these no sequel data stores
along yet another axis which is how they
distribute data across a grid or cluster
where the main representative models in
that accident yes that is true
so there's some different ways to scale
out in these systems one method that was
popularized by Anna
on which they originally built in their
internal dynamo product was used
consistent hashing where you basically
put things out on a hash ring and then
that determines what servers they live
on and what servers they live on if
servers fail so that's one model of
distribution it's really the consistent
hashing family of solutions the other
model is auto shortening and that was
popularized by Google with BigTable so
in this model we basically take a bunch
of data that we want to partition and we
define key ranges which are like chunks
of data that say maybe 100 megabytes in
size and we keep metadata on those
chunks and we just remember oh yeah all
the data in this key range is on shard
29 and and then the system does that and
there are pros and cons of the two
approaches what would be a couple of key
points in favor of the one or the other
so the consistent hashing is I think
it's it's elegant and simple so is one
of the strengths it's very clear how to
add new nodes to the system and how to
take them away so it's very clean in
that sense the the author sharding I
think it's a pretend perhaps a little
more complex to implement but the main
thing to get there is we get order
preserving partitioning right so keys
that are close to each other will tend
to be on the same machine so if you're
doing a range query that can be
important and and that would be
difficult to do with a consistent
hashing system looking at these systems
this is something I'm trying to wrap my
head around and I haven't really figured
out I see that you can have something
like Voldemort which is a key value
store it's an a class system and it uses
the Amazon model of data distribution
and then you have DB which is
document based and it's using the auto
sharding model and it's a C class system
and I just pick one from column a one
from column B one from column C and get
all the properties I want order these
three axes somehow constrain each other
the two to a large degree you can pick
and choose so you could say I want this
this and this and now I'm gonna go write
the system the system I'm aware of its
most comparable to MongoDB as couchdb at
least in the terms of the storage model
how would you compare and yeah so
they're there in some ways they're
similar
so they're both JSON databases which i
think is a good thing they they're both
pretty rich in functionality and
features so they're both towards the
high functionality end of the spectrum
in the space there the way you talk to
and use the systems is quite different
so couch uses an rest interface to talk
to the database whereas in we use
a native proprietary wire protocol to
talk to the database just like a
traditional database so we actually have
a client for every programming language
that you can talk to it uses this
proprietary wire protocol and the reason
we did that was for efficiency so we
wanted to build something that was kind
of very exact to what we needed to do
over the protocol rather than the use
rest so it was purely for a performance
reason because otherwise rest would be
nice because it's just a nice standard
format so that's a difference in
addition the way queries work is quite
different between the two systems in
couch to define a query you basically
create a view which is defined by a set
of map and reduce functions and then it
materializes that view effectively so
that is extremely elegant and nice but
it does mean you have to pre declare
these views and we actually do
more traditional ad-hoc queries so you
give the database a query in the
query language which is actually JSON
basically we then run it through a query
optimizer generate a query plan and run
the query and you can declare indexes
just like in a traditional my sequel
database so that's a more traditional
approach but the nice thing there as I
get ad-hoc queries other differences are
couch is very good at master master
replication with resynchronization after
being offline for a long period of time
so if you wanted to write Lotus Notes
couchdb would be really good at that
because that's sort of an online offline
sync up problem is more oriented
towards problems where you want a
stronger consistency model and you don't
want to write code yourself around
version reconciliation on merges of
master master replication things like
that maybe things where you want global
state like you want to create a unique
key index which would be problematic
with math or master master replication
so I think it works really well for
building say Web Apps for example
there's a sweet spot for it
couch is written in Erlang is
written in C++ that's another difference
clearly MongoDB has a much richer set of
operations that can do on the server
than a key value store yes I must be
paying something in order to get them
because why wouldn't you want to have
all that query capability free that's a
great question so our opinion is that
you're not it's not going to cost you
much right so these both these BigTable
data model systems and the
document-oriented and JSON systems
obviously they can represent key value
style data that's a subset of the
problems they can represent so then the
question is just about are they a lot
slower or am i losing something like
that and I don't think you're losing
that much I think it's a very small hit
you're taking on performance
you know our philosophy is we think as
you add features to the database at some
point it gets slower and less scalable
but we think there's an e in that curve
we think you can add quite a bit of
functionality and but when you hit a
certain point if you go any further
you're gonna get 10x slower so we're
trying to fish as far over towards that
knee as we can and no further so you
know we want to kind of get to 75 80
percent of the functionality of a
traditional database yet had these very
interesting new properties in terms of
speed scale and ease of development and
so we're going to leave out a couple
things but we're not going to leave out
percent of the stuff which is kind of if
you go pure pure key-value what you're
doing how's the MongoDB open-source
project organized with 10gen as the
sponsor yeah so it's open source you
know it's on github the attention we
actually started the project originally
but now there are outside contributors
in a very active community there are
other companies who are building
businesses around MongoDB right now such
as HQ which is another company
that's doing cloud-based hosting and
which is just using the open
source project so you know it's open
source we we love open source and we
want lots of people participating in the
community and doing commits and other
good things what are some areas where
the community is especially active in
contributing add-ons so a few areas I
think there's been a lot of drivers
written by the community there's also
been data frameworks that said above the
drivers written by the community like
the mapper we discussed earlier
it's written by the community
there have been administrative UI is
written by the community and then the
community works on the core database -
and in addition documentation a lot of
people make contributions to the docs
translate the docs and other languages
so there's and and and just also
evangelism training all these things -
they can email info at Tenjin com if
they want to get involved and we'll help
them
it could also jump on the MongoDB IRC
channel and chat with people in real
time and get involved and and we'd love
that what are some interesting features
of people should expect in upcoming
releases of the server the one for
release so the even release numbers are
the stable releases so those are the
ones you really care about the one for
release which is out now one of the big
additions there was geospatial indexing
which is nice if you're doing mobile
apps you really need that the one six
release which will be out the summer is
all about scaling so production sharding
and a new release of replication will
out in the one six release which will
really make true production quality
large cluster as possible so
that's what all the work today is about
then in the fall there will be work on
some other things including single
server durability with a new storage
engine work on MapReduce increased
performance work on full-text search and
things like that not it I'm not sure the
exact dates on all of those but that's
what's in the in the roadmap going out
further people are interested in
following you do you log yes so if you
go to the Tenjin site in the about page
you'll see links to my blog and twitter
my twitter is DM er rd mayor on twitter
how many people are using MongoDB the
uptake recently has been fantastic so in
March there were 37 thousand downloads
of the database and that does not count
drivers or Docs or anything like that so
that's a pretty clean number which we
think is great for where this market is
at this point and that's up you know six
months ago that number was ten times
smaller so we're really seeing very nice
pick up and usage of the product you
know people like Foursquare are using
the product now and SourceForge github
new york times so it's really exciting
and I think the usages you have any kind
of semi scientific data about market
share of no sequel in the data store
market yeah so it's it's still small but
there's a clear trend here it's
definitely happening it's gonna happen
you know we're at a conference here
today with 200 people that sold out here
in San Francisco that's only about
MongoDB not much so you know if you
project out for the whole no sequel
space you know you're starting to get a
lot of activity I think you know in the
web space I think by the end of this
year you know it'll be more people will
if they're starting to build a new web
app will use a no sequel solution
use a traditional relational solution
now that's for a web app right so that's
not in total right because that's the
early adopter use case for no sequel so
we're getting to the point where it's
gonna be quite significant but of course
you've got this big big install base of
relational right so even if we get all
of these no sequel solutions to very
high you know number of downloads per
month you know it still takes you know
say 30 months before you that starts to
add up into a lot of apps being out
there and things being written on them
Dwight Merriman thank you very much for
speaking to software engineering radio
thank you thanks for listening to
software engineering radio software
engineer radio is an educational program
brought to you by hillside Europe if you
want more information about the podcast
and all the other episodes visit our
website at se - radio dotnet if you want
to support us you can donate to the AC
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash top button to
contact the team please send email to
team @ SC - radio net or if they're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the port side music network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas Achtung